Okay, so today we are doing Julius Caesar and the fall of the Roman Republic.
好的，今天我们来讲朱利叶·凯撒与罗马共和国的衰落。
Julius Caesar is considered the greatest historical figure of all time.
朱利叶·凯撒被认为是史上最伟大的人物。
He's also one of the most controversial.
他也是最具争议的之一。
Okay, so today we're gonna look at three questions about his life
好的，今天我们要先看三条关于他的一点。
and I want to provide an argument about his life.
我想给出一个好点的说法。
Okay, so the first question we're gonna look at is what did he want?
好的，先前一条。
What were his motivations for what he did?
...
Did he want to become a king of Rome or was he trying to save the Roman Republic?
Okay, so this is a historical debate that's been around for us for about 2,000 years
...
and no one has resolved it.
}]
Second question I want to look at is why was he
? 1? 1????..??..???…..??…..………?…..??……………?…..…………?………………..???…..………..?……………..?…..………..?…..…..??……………..?………… 1..???…..………..?…………??…..?…………..???..…………..?…………..?…..………..?……………..…………..?…..……..…………..
so successful at what he did?
.??..???…..??..……?…..……..…..??..??..……..…?…..……
I mean he was a man who basically took on the Roman Empire
...
and he won. Okay, so how was he able to accomplish that?
So many many many many many many many many many many many many many
...
many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many
many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many
...
many many many many many many many many many many many many many
many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many
...
many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many Okay,
多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多多
so why did they kill him? All right, so
...
my central argument to you today is
that Julius Caesar was so successful
...
because he was a myth maker,
因为他是个神话制造者，
a myth maker.
因为他是个神话制造者。
A myth maker are individuals who
译文1
change the course of human history because
译...
they see themselves as a man of destiny
他们看着自己是命运之人
who must change the world for the better
...
and they do so
...?????????????????????????????
by constructing a new reality
...????..??..??..??..???
that begins to absorb the old reality
and alters it, okay?
And they do so
...
through their words,
their speeches, their writings, and through their actions.
他们的演讲、他们的文字以及他们的行动。
So they see themselves as the main character, the protagonists
...
in a novel that they are writing.
All right, so this is a hard concept to understand,
翻译：
but let's use some examples to better understand this concept.
但让我们用一些例子来更好地理解这个概念。
So the first example, let's look at is the idea of Steve Jobs.
好的，先看一条例子，先前往前的那条。”
Steve Jobs was an entrepreneur,
史蒂夫·乔布斯是一位企业家，
but he was first and foremost a myth maker, okay?
So Steve Jobs,
好的，先看一条例子，先前往前的上条
the joke about Steve Jobs was Steve Jobs had a secret weapon.
好的，先前往前的条
It was called a reality distortion projector.
它被称为“现实投影机”
Basically, Steve Jobs lied to people.
基本上，史蒂夫·乔布…
But he lied to people in such an appealing manner,
但他以如此吸引人的方式撒了谣，
in such a beautiful way that it changed the reality.
在此处…
Basically, Steve Jobs imposed his reality onto others.
基本上，史蒂夫·乔布把自己的现实投射到别人身上。
And today, that's why we use Apple computers, right?
今天，没错?
We all have Apple computers.
??
Why do we do this?
???
Because we are participating in the myth
that Steve Jobs created for us, right?
那是个……………………??………………………??………??……??………
That if you use Apple computers, you are using the most advanced technology, and
]}We need to translate cues [55] and [56] into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSON with translations array of two strings. Use natural Chinese. Let's translate: cue 55:
you are participating in a pleasing lifestyle.
你们正好好地去做了个好好地...??……??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??……??…??…??………
Okay, so it's about technology, but it's also about lifestyle, it's also about attitude.
??
And that's why we are all using Apple computers today,
???
because we are trying to participate in this myth, okay?
Another example is the idea of movies, right?
另一个例子是电影的概念，………??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…外…???????
Movies are reality creation machines.
???????????????????????????????????
When you go see a movie, if it's a really good movie,
当你去看电影时，若是好电影，...??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…??…
it will stick in your mind, and
]}We need to translate cues [63] and [64] into Simplified Chinese. The given translation for [63] is incomplete. We need to produce JSON with translations array of two strings. Each string may contain at most one newline. Use preferred terms. Let's translate: cue 63:
it will change the way you perceive reality,
??
okay? So someone like Julius Caesar, what he was trying to do in his life
was create a new narrative
was create a newnarrative
that would redefine reality.
The last example I want to use, and
??
I'm really sorry for using this example,
is Donald Trump, right?
??
Because Donald Trump wants to make America great again.
因为...
And so for his speeches and for his actions,
???
he's trying to construct or conceive
a new understanding of America
一个新的美国理解
that absorbs the imagination of everyone around him.
吸收了他周围的人的想法
Does that make sense? That's what a myth maker is.
77. 译文1
And that's why, ultimately, Julius Caesar was
...
so successful, okay?
???
But the problem with being a myth maker is,
]}We need to translate [79] and [80]. We have previous context. We need to produce JSON with translations array of two strings. Use simplified Chinese. Let's translate. [79]
by creating new myths, you are disrupting old myths
通过创造新神话，你正在打乱旧神话
that people rely on for their understanding of the world.
You're creating something called cognitive dissonance.
你正在创造一种叫作业的...
And people don't like cognitive dissonance.
...
It makes them uncomfortable. So they killed Julius Caesar
It makes them uncomfortable.So they killed Julius Caesar
because his new myth of Rome
...
was surpassing the old myth of Rome, and that
]}We need to translate cue [87] English:
made the old guard uncomfortable, and
让它们感到舒适…
that's why they had to kill him, all right?
...
So that's my argument to you today. All right,
so now that I've made the general argument, let me provide some historical background
...
so we understand the historical context
that Julius Caesar was operating in, okay?
So let's go back to 216.
So let's go backto 216.
Last class, we talked about 216 BCE, and
this was the Hannibal invasion of Rome.
...
And remember, at the Battle of Cannae,
Rome lost about 20% of its adult male population.
罗马失去约20%的成年男性人口。
And at this point, Rome should have surrendered or negotiated peace terms.
在此时，罗马应该有点儿…
But Rome instead chose to fought on, and it fought on
...
because it had a mythology about itself
that was based on three principles, right?
那是基于三项原则的，没错吗？
The three principles are piety,
三项原则是：敬…
liberty, and republica.
自由与共和国。
And because of these three principles,
???
every Roman felt he or she
每个罗马人都觉得自己要作出终极献祭以拯罗马
had to make the ultimate sacrifice in order to save Rome, okay?
每个罗马古里...
And so everyone made a sacrifice.
108. 译文：...???????????????????????????????????????????
The rich, made sacrifices by basically paying for the war,
?
okay? Also the rich freed their slaves
OK? 先后?????????????先后????????????? 先后??…
so that slaves could become citizens in order to fight for Rome.
??
The poor also made a lot of sacrifices
...
because they had to fight in the army,
but also because the way the Romans decided to defeat Hannibal
]
and it worked is something we call a scorched earth policy.
翻译：
Scorched earth policy. Basically,
make the land unfarmable.
??
So then your army has no access to food, okay?
...
And that's how the ultimate defeated Hannibal, because they burned all the land
翻译结果
and they couldn't grow food on the land, and so
and they couldn't growfood on the land, and so
Hannibal's army could not feed itself, okay?
汉尼拔的军队没能自给粮食，行吗？
So everyone made the ultimate sacrifice.
于是大家都做了最好的回报。
The rich fought, the rich and the poor fought alike.
富人战斗，富人与富人战斗。”
The rich paid for the war, the poor lost their land,
...
okay? And this was all possible
okay? 这就是...
because of the nature of Rome at that time.
...
Remember, Rome at that time was poor,
记得，罗马当时很小，大家都相互知晓。
very small place where everyone knew each other,
记得罗马当时很小，大家相互相知。
and ultimately it was threatened with existence,
翻译后...
okay? Hannibal proved to be an existential threat to Rome
...
and that's why everyone became united.
}]
And made the ultimate sacrifice, okay?
...
And for Romans, this was the finest hour.
This was the moment they celebrated
...
when their very existence was threatened by Hannibal,
when their very existencewas threatened by Hannibal,
but they came together and made the ultimate sacrifice
...
and ultimately defeated Hannibal.
并最终击败了汉尼拔。
The problem was this. The problem was after Rome won the war,
问题在于此。 这就是后...
the question then is who got the rewards, right?
问题是，谁得到了奖励？
Everyone made the sacrifice, the poor lost their land, the rich lost their money.
每个人都做了牺牲，大家都没得…
And because the rich controlled the government,
因为富人掌握政府，
remember, Rome is a republic, it's not a democracy,
it was decided the rich would get
它决定富人得到
most of the rewards of the war.
它们的...
In fact, the poor got very little. So
在此处……
an example here is the idea of common land.
…
Common land is what do you do with the new territory
翻译1
that you conquer in Spain and
翻译2
from the Carthaginian Empire?
来自卡尔塔格帝国吗？
And normally,
通常是这样，
common land would be given to everyone, right?
公共土地会给每个人，没错吧？
Maybe in proportion, but it would be given to everyone,
也许按比例，但会分给每个人，
especially the poor who lost their land.
尤其是失去土地的贫民，
But Rome made the decision that
但罗马作决定后，
the rich would be compensated
富人将得到补偿
for letting money to the republic during the war,
为让出钱给共和国在战时
meaning the rich got the lion's share of the new land.
意为富人获得新土地的领头
But not only that, the remaining common land,
但不只是这样，剩余的公共土地，
the rich just pretended it was theirs, okay?
富人只是假装它是自己的，好吗？
Meaning that they illegally occupied common land.
意思是他们把它占为公有的土地。
They didn't pay for it, it wasn't theirs, but they just assumed it was theirs.
...
And so now Rome had a problem.
Rome was great, it was poor and
...
small, it was threatened by its neighbors like the Tristians, the Carthaginians, and the Greeks.
小的，它被邻国如特里斯人、迦特加人和希腊人所威胁。
But by 146 BCE,
但在公元前146年，
Rome had vanquished all its major enemies.
罗马已胜利所有大敌。
And basically it was an empire.
基本上它是一个帝国。
And by 146, Rome had become a contradiction.
在公元前146年，罗马已成为一场大冲突。
Okay? The contradiction is this.
好的？这就是它的冲突。
It is an imperial republic.
它是一个帝制共和国。
Okay? It is an empire now, but its form of government is a republic.
好的，先前是个帝制共和国。
And this was a contradiction.
它是个帝制共和国。”
And suddenly, these three values, okay?
...
Piety, liberty, and republica,
these values that made Rome strong
...
were now problems. Okay?
And so now, we're going to talk about the problems for the Roman people.
...
Okay? So let me explain how.
Let's look at Republica. Republica means public virtue in Latin.
让我们来看看共和国。共和国在拉丁语里有“公民”之意。
It's the idea that the best and
它是个好好??
brightest in Rome are in competition with each other
??
to promote the Roman national welfare,
为了促进罗马国民福利，
okay? To bring glory to Rome.
好吧，拉个百事...??
That's, if you were the best and the brightest, then you're a great person.
...
And many people came to Rome and came to Rome to serve as a residence.
和许多人来到罗马，去做住居。
And many came to Rome to serve as residence. And many came to Rome to serve as residence.
和许多人去罗马去做住居。
And many came to Rome to serve as residence.
和许多人去罗马去…
和许多人来到罗马去做住居。
And many came to Rome to serve as residence. And many came to Rome to serve as residence.
和许多人来到罗马去做住居。和许多人去罗马去…
和许多人去罗马去…
And many came to Rome to serve as residence.
和许多人去罗马去做住居。
和许多人来到罗马去做住居。
to be promoted. But now that you have money,
去晋升。 但现在有钱后，能做的就是去给人打点儿…
what you realize you could do is just bribe people, okay?
And then so very soon,
然后，...
bribery just became a fact of politics in Rome.
brib...
Once you won political office, you can then
...
become a general to go off to provinces
成为将军去征服省份
to fight wars to win new territory for Rome,
去战斗去争取罗马新地
okay? But because you got into so much debt
好吧？ 归还要算算债务
to win the political office,
赢得政治职务，
when you went to a province, you did two things.
当你去到省份时，做了两件事。
First of all, you exploited the local people, okay?
先行先...
Because you need to get back that money that you spent.
因为你需要把花费的那笔钱拿回来。
The second thing that you did was you start wars for no reason, okay?
第二个是我方在先前的……
You antagonize the locals in order to start wars.
先前……??
If you start wars, you win a lot of money, right?
如果你发动战争，你就能赢得大量金钱，没错吧？
You can enslave the people and make money that way.
你可以把人们变成奴隶，继续把…
But also, you will receive something called a triumph, okay?
“可是…………??
Triumph. Now triumph is just a military parade
胜利。现在胜利只是一次军事游行
that establishes you as a hero of Rome.
胜利之于...
And not only do you benefit politically, but your entire family benefits, okay?
胜利之...
So your sons, your grandsons,
所以你的小儿子、孙子、曾孙子……
your great -grandsons will all be remembered
...
and celebrated because of your triumph.
And they are much more likely to,
和...
when they get back, to win political office, okay, in their careers, okay?
...
So the triumph is a very, very big thing.
The problem is,
问题是，
while the best and brightest were in competition with each other,
当最优秀的选手相互竞争时，
the poor were suffering, okay?
贫穷人家却在受苦。
So the first problem is land.
所以第一个问题是土地。
Remember, during the Hannibal Wars, the Second Punic War,
记得哈尼巴尔战争期间，第二次布尔战争…
the poor lost a lot of land,
...
and they were never compensated for it.
并且在此期间，...
But then what happened is, as Rome was continuing to fight these wars,
...
the poor was being drafted into the army,
and they were going to like Spain and Syria.
230: 1/2/???
These are faraway places, and they were stuck there for like years.
?????????????……
That meant their land couldn't be cultivated,
………
and therefore they got into debt.
并且他们获得了债务。
And they couldn't pay off the debt, so what happened was the rich would come in
又可归一百百…
and buy off the land at very cheap prices, okay?
先前…
And so the rich became major land owners.
又是富人变成了大地主。
And there's a problem because first of all,
先前…
the poor didn't have any land in order to grow food,
so they were forced into the cities, okay?
于是他们被迫搬到城里，行吗？
Their problem is the rich didn't want to grow food to feed the people,
他们的困境是富人不愿意种粮食来供给人们，行吗？
right? They wanted to grow food as cash crops for export.
他们想要种作物种作物，作作…
So suddenly for the first time in its history, Rome couldn't feed itself.
于是，罗马在其历史上第一次出现了粮食自给不足的情况。
You have to rely on imports from the provinces,
你们要把它们从省份里搬到回到本地，
okay?
好的？
So the land was a huge issue.
译文1
But then you also had issues like debt, right? So
译前后翻译结果
the poor couldn't pay off their debts,
]}We need to translate cues 245-247 into Simplified Chinese. Provide JSON array translations. Each string may contain at most one newline. Use terms: land power=陆权. But cue 245:
and they became overwhelmed by interest.
...
And so this created lots of problems for Rome, okay?
...??????...
So you had a lot of violence, you have a lot of corruption,
...????..??????????????????..??..?????..?????..??..?????..??..?????..?????..?????..????????..?????..??...????????..??..?????..??..???..??..?????..??..?????..??..?????..?????..??..?????..??..?????..??..?????..??..?????..??..?????..??..???..???……………………………
you have a lot of inequality,
???
okay? And
...
so this started a cycle
that Peter Churchill calls elite overproduction, right?
在此时，...
So in times of peace, and as your population grows,
...
you're gonna have too many elite who are now in competition with each other.
And it's usually between the upper nobility
...
and the lower nobility, okay?
So upper nobility are people who are established.
上层贵族是已建立的贵族。
They're the wealthiest citizens in all of Rome.
他们是罗马全城最富有的公民。
They're very happy with the system as it is.
他们很高兴地接受了现有的系统。
The lower nobility are people who are born into wealth, but they want more.
下层贵族出生时就有财富，但又想要更多。
They want prestige, they want honor, they want the triumph.
他们想要荣誉，想要…
And so they're struggling against the upper nobility
...
for political power. And usually you do
为政治权力。通常你会通过与人们结盟来实现。
that by aligning yourself with the people, right?
And the people who
和现在数以百万的民众已愤怒，
are now number in the millions are pissed off because
they have no land, they're too much in debt, and no jobs, okay?
他们有土地吗？...??
And so these two factions in Rome, we'd call, the upper nobility we'd call the optimates.
...??
Okay, optimates just means best people.
好的，优化者只是指最优秀的人。
We're the best. And
我们是最好的，且…
our responsibility is to uphold to tradition of Rome,
我们的工作是把…
which is pious. liberty, and republica.
哪一条是“pious”呢？自由、自由之…
And these people with low nobility who
...
wanted to change, they're called populaires.
And that's where we get the term populist from.
并且在此处我们得到了“民粹”一词。
So in 146 BCE,
在 146 年前后，
after Rome had become an empire and had defeated all its enemies,
在 先前后，
these two factions start to emerge and
这些两派开始出现并且相互冲突。
they clash with each other.
随后，历史学家认为第一次冲突是与格拉奇兄弟相冲突。
So historians normally believe the first clash happened with the Gracchi brothers,
So historians normally believe the firstclash happened with the Gracchi brothers,
the Gracchus brothers.
格拉奇兄弟
And these are, again, low nobility who had a very simple idea, land reform.
低级贵族的土地改革方案
The idea is very simple.
该方案很简单。
You have rich people who have too much land
你们有富人拥有太多土地
and not used the land properly.
他人们的土地没能好好地去做…
They're using the land as parks for themselves, as like these private parks for themselves,
?
or they're growing crash crops, which does not feed well.
...
And they're not using the land properly. And they're not using the land as a home. Most of this land, which
is again common land, the rich are occupying it illegally,
...
is not being used productively.
292. 该句子句...??
So what they proposed was a simple land reform law.
???
And the idea is this. Rome, the government of Rome,
would buy out the rich from the land they are illegally occupying.
会买回富人占据的土地。
Does that make sense?
这点吗？
The rich won't be kicked out the land they're illegally occupying.
富人会占据的土地
They'll be compensated for it.
他们会得到补偿。
So this makes perfect sense.
这就好像个完好。”
Not a problem, right? And once Rome buys out this land, it will then redistribute it to the poor.
...
So the poor will have like a social safety system.
They were able to feed themselves.
...
And they'll usually grow grain
and other crops for sustenance.
和其他作物以供食用。
And this will enable the feeding of the Roman population in general.
并且能让罗马人总之吃
Okay. So this sounds very simple to us.
好的，先说一句：是的！
But the rich didn't like this idea because they didn't like change in the land.
OK
They didn't like the idea of the land being distributed to the poor. They like the idea of piety,
他们不想把土地分给穷人。他们想要分配给...
liberty and republica, which
...
means things must stay the way they are.
意思是要把事情保持在原来那样。
And what's really important is the rich cannot be challenged by the poor.
而且要把…
Because if that were the case, then the social system would be overhauled.
...
So the rich were so pissed off
that they assassinated both brothers, the Gracchi brothers.
那时，大家把它们放在了…
And most historians believe this is the beginning of the fall of the Roman republic.
...
So many people have no right to have a right to have because it tells us that
316. 许多…
the system is incapable of change.
?
The system as it's set up, which focuses on piety,
…
liberty, and republica, it's a contradiction now,
自由...
and this contradiction cannot be internally resolved.
So any more questions?
自由...
Any questions before I proceed on?
任何问题吗？
I know this is a lot, and maybe I haven't organized it properly,
我知道这很大…
but are there any confusions about this history so far?
...
Again, I'm just providing some background and context before I move on to do this either.
再次，我只是先给一些背景和上下文再来回到…
Yeah? Okay.
好的，…
Yeah, this is a great question. What's the relationship between optimists and the populaires?
…
There's exactly 20 noble families in Rome.
有20个贵族家族在罗马。
And so these people, the optimists and
...
the populaires, all come from these 20 noble families.
And they're like cousins of each other.
他们像相互相亲的表兄弟。
So the optimists are maybe like the fathers and
于是可见此时可归为…
the grandfathers, and the populaires are like the sons.
其…
Does that make sense? Right?
那算得了吗？对吗？
Because the fathers don't want any change,
因为…
but the sons want political power.
...
And so they're all related.
于是他们相互相亲。
They all grew up with each other.
他们都一起成长。
They all know each other. Okay?
他们都相互相知。
Does that make sense? Okay.
那算得了吗？好吧。
All right. Eko, are you good?
好了，Eko，你好了吗？
Is this clear to you so far? All right.
到目前为止，已知晓吗？
All right. So the first major conflict is the Gracchi brothers.
好的。第一个主要冲突是格拉奇兄弟。
Second major conflict that happens, is something called a social war.
第二个主要冲突是个别名叫“社交”之战。
And the social war is basically this.
而且是个别名的…
The people who fight the wars are the allies,
战斗者是罗马的同盟，意大利之盟友。
the Italian allies of Rome.
好的，意大利之盟友。
Okay? People who live in the neighboring provinces.
好吧！
They're the ones who fight the war. And after Rome keeps on winning these wars,
他们是战斗者。随后罗马不断胜战。
Rome refuses to grant citizenship to them.
罗马不再给他人们的回归。
Okay? So these neighbors rebel.
好吧！
And there's a civil war going on in Rome.
...
And Rome loses this war. And
Rome is forced to grant
...
citizenship to these neighbors.
给这些邻居回归。
But the question then is, what is the nature of citizenship?
但…
Like how much rights do you get?
像这样，你获得了多少权利？
How much power do you get?
你获得了多少个回归？
Because Rome is a republic.
因为罗马是个共和国。
And so one thing that's hard for us to understand is not all voters are equal.
而且…
Okay? So if you're a rich voter,
好的？如果你是个富裕选民，你就有更大的投票权。
you have more power than if you are a poor voter.
好的，? …】
Okay? So the question then is, these new citizens of Rome,
好的？那么问题是，罗马的新公民会有哪种投票权？
what sort of voting rights will they have?
好的，...
And this is an issue that became a huge issue over the next few decades.
和这件事在接下来几百年里变成了大事
Okay? So the social war. Then you have these slave revolts.
这是一个在接下来几百年里出现的“…”，但…
What they call the Servile Wars.
什么叫“Servile”战争
Okay? Then
好的，...
you have these piracy going on.
好的...
Okay? So Rome,
好的？所以罗马，罗马共和国不断地动荡与冲突。好的？和…
the Roman Republic, is constantly in turmoil and in conflict.
好的？罗马的...
Okay? And the war between the optimists and
好的...
the populists becomes so intense that
人马的民粹者的军队变得如此激烈，
ultimately they fight a civil war.
最终他们会打起了“自”式的战斗。
Okay? A civil war means two armies killing each other.
好的，...
Okay? And so
好的？于是…
the civil war was between Sulla and
好的，...
Marius.
好的...
And the civil war becomes more intense.
和内战变得更激烈。
And it becomes so intense that both Sulla and Marius do the unthinkable
而且……
and they march their armies into Rome and kill their enemies.
...
This has never been done in Roman history before.
这在罗马历史上第一次出现。
As a general, you're not supposed to take your soldiers and
作为一名士兵，士兵们…
march against your own government, against your own city, and kill your own people.
...
Okay? But that's what they both do. Sulla wins the civil war.
好的？但这就是他们两人所做的。苏拉赢了内战。
And he understands, like all Romans, that Rome is a civil war.
而且…
This can't go on.
这回归…
Okay? There has to be a solution. And
OK? 需要有个方案。
Sulla's solution is, well,
OK? 方案 … …
you know, if the problem is the conflict between the populists
?
and the optimists, let's just kill all the populists.
和优化者一起，先把所有民粹者杀了吧。
And then the problem will be solved.
然后再把……
Then you have stability in Rome.
…
Okay? And this is what we refer to as proscription.
好的？这就是我们所说的“追剿”
Proscription. And proscription means this.
追剿。它就是这样：
There's a list, a public list of about, you know, about the people that are in Rome.
有一份公开名单，列出罗马里的人数
There's about a thousand, two thousand, okay, individuals.
有大约一千二千个…
And these individuals are basically sanctioned to be killed.
...
So if you go kill them,
…
you'll be rewarded by the state and
你会被国家奖励，随后给你分配给你所杀的那几个人的财产。
you'll be given the property of those you killed.
你会被...
Okay? And it's called proscription.
...
And this is a new invention by Sulla in order to resolve the conflict between the optimists
and the populists. One of those individuals
...
who was designated to be proscribed,
his name is Julius Caesar.
他的名字是朱利斯·凯撒。
And he's about 19 years old now. Okay? And
他大约19岁。
Julius Caesar comes from a very prestigious Roman family called the Julii.
朱利斯·凯撒来自一个非常有名望的罗马之家。
And he's the nephew of Marius.
翻译1
And that's why he was, he was proscribed.
]}
Okay? Now, the good thing is,
?
if you're rich, you can bribe your way out of these things.
如果你富有，便可以贿赎之道脱身。
Okay? And Julius Caesar's family was extremely wealthy.
朱利斯·凯撒家族极其富裕。
And he was able to bribe Sulla into letting him go.
他能以贿赎给Sulla让他去。
Okay? So Julius Caesar's life was speared.
译文1
And Sulla believed that
译?????????????????????????????????????????????????
by doing this, by killing off the populiers,
?
by making the optimists the supreme power in the land, this conflict would go away.
通过把优化器放在土地的最高权力之中，...
But after Sulla died,
...
this didn't happen.
Okay? In fact, the conflict became even worse.
好的？事实上，冲突更…
Okay? So
好的，...
Julius Caesar grew up in this conflict.
...
Right? He grew up in a time of the imperial republic, a contradiction.
424. 右？他在帝国共和国的时代成长，出现了…
And he saw himself as the man of destiny
]}
to save the republic by implementing
?
the reforms necessary in
在恢复罗马稳定所需的改革
order to restore
在恢复罗马的...
stability in Rome.
在…
Okay? He basically wanted to make Rome great again.
好的？他基本想让罗马再次伟大。
Any questions so far? Is this all clear to you guys?
还有什么问题吗？到此为止？
Okay? All right.
“好”~??
So let's talk about the life of Julius Caesar.
让我们来聊聊朱利叶·凯撒的生平
Okay? From an early age,
好的，先从头开始！
Julius Caesar saw himself as special.
朱利叶·朱撒”??
But not only that, but from an early age,
但不止于此，早在少年时，朱利叶·凯撒很关心他的人民。
Julius Caesar cared a lot about his people.
朱利叶·凯撒很关心他的人民。
He cared about public image. He cared about how people perceived and remembered him.
他在意外观形象，且在意其人们的回忆。”]}We need to translate cues 436-438. Provide translations arraywith 3 strings. Ensure Chinese natural. Use preferred terms. Let's craft. Cue 436:
Okay? So here's a story to highlight the
译文1
myth -making genius of Julius Caesar.
译文2
Okay? So when Julius Caesar was 25,
译文3
he was sent off to Anatolia to work as an official there.
译文1
Now, the problem with sailing at this time is there's a lot of piracy.
译文2
Right? Because there's a lot of corruption, inequality,
译作
and piracy. And there's a lot of poverty in the empire.
和海盗。帝国里有很多贫困。
And so when he was 25, Julius Caesar was kidnapped,
当他25岁时，朱利叶·凯撒被绑架，
captured and kidnapped by pirates.
当时的朱利叶·凯撒被海盗抓住并且
Not a big deal because he's of the nobility.
他是个大事，没什么大事，...
And it's obvious he's of the nobility.
...
And so the pirates asked for a ransom.
They started to pay the ransom.
他们开始支付赎金。
And Julius Caesar was free to go.
朱利叶·凯撒自由去了。
Okay? Now, very simple story.
好的？现在，简单的故事。
But what Julius Caesar did was he embelished a story.
但朱利叶·凯撒所做的事是他把故事装饰了一番。
Okay? He made certain adjustments to the story that made it memorable.
好的？他把某些调整放进了故事里，让它变得记得住。
Okay? He made certain adjustments to people so that people would discuss it everywhere.
好的？把这点儿 … … …
Okay? The first embellishment he made was this.
好的？他做的第一个装饰是这个。
The pirates asked for a 20 silver talent ransom.
海盗们请求了20个银才的赎金。
Okay? Which is a lot of money.
好的？这就是一笔大钱。
And Julius Caesar said, when I heard this, I felt insulted.
和朱利叶·凯撒说，听到这句………
How dare you ask for 20 silver talents?
...…… 好吧！………
I'm worth at least 50.
…… 好吧……
Okay? So, hey guys, don't ask for 20.
好的？所以，伙计们，别再要20了。
Ask for 50. My family can afford it.
再来一次，给我点儿百个?
Okay? So that's the first embellishment.
先前? 先前? ??
The second embellishment he made was Julius Caesar said,
第二个夸张的说法是朱利叶·凯撒说，我与海盗相识。
I became friends with the pirates.
我与海盗相识后，咱们一起喝酒。
We drank together. He's a very charismatic individual.
他是一位很有魅力的…
And I told them while we were drinking, hey guys,
...
after I go home, I'm going to come back and
capture all of you and crucify every one of you.
...
And the pirates are like, that's really funny, man.
Okay? So that's the second embellishment.
...
The third embellishment is Julius Caesar,
after he was released, he set up a navy and he went
after ... ... ... ... ... ...... ... ... ... ... JSON ... ?
and found every one of these pirates and crucified every one of them.
...
Okay? And that's the third embellishment because
we actually don't know if he actually did this.
...
But again, the thing that
Julius Caesar understands is it doesn't matter
...
if the facts are true or not.
What matters is how appealing are the details.
什么才是关键：细节的吸引力。
Right? So this story,
是的? 这条??????????????????????????????????????????????????????
you'll remember forever and you will tell others about it.
你会永记住它，并且会把它告诉别人。
So through this, he's creating a myth of himself.
通过这件事， 你们把它们的 …
Does that make sense? And
那算得了？再说，这几件事都不算是个好时机！
again, there's no way any of these things are true.
那算得了？再说…
Right? He's like, oh, 20 talents.
右？他像，20才子。
I'm insulted. Ask for 50 guys.
我…
Okay? And while he's drinking with these guys, and these are pirates, these are like psychopaths.
好的？他在和这些人喝酒时，酒鬼们又是个…
Right? He's like, I'm going to come back and kill every one of you.
...
Every one of you. But again,
每一个人。再说，那就是朱利叶·凯撒的神话创造天才。
that's the myth -making genius of Julius Caesar.
that's the myth -makinggenius of Julius Caesar.
So, again, as a young man,
所以，重新回到…
the greatest honor in Rome is to achieve the triumph.
...
And you do that by starting wars.
并且通过起战来完成此事。
So, through bribery and through charisma,
通过 … 的 … 来回到…
Caesar is elected a praetor.
先前……
And then as a praetor, he goes off to Spain.
作为一名执政官，他前往西班牙。
He fights these wars against the tribes of Spain.
他在西班牙与之战斗的斗争。
And then he wins a triumph.
随后他赢得了胜利之战
Okay? And
好的？然后
what he wants to do is he wants
他想要的就是…
to basically use the triumph as the springboard for his
他把…
political career, to win the consulship.
政治生涯，赢得执政官职位。
At this point, okay,
此时，好的，
the optimists hate Julius Caesar.
优化者们爱上了朱利叶·凯撒。
Because Julius Caesar, again, he's a myth -making genius.
因为朱利奥·凯撒再次出现，...
He's telling all these stories. And it's pissing off the optimists.
...
Because they see Julius Caesar as, you know,
as he's just a braggart.
他是个大自夸者。
Okay? He's arrogant. He just brags all the time.
好的，...
He's appeasing the people.
他在此时...
He's exactly what Romans should not be.
他正是罗马人应有的那种人。
Okay? He's impious. He doesn't care for liberty.
好的，...
He doesn't care about the public good. All he cares about is his own personal glory.
他不再...
When he's got a reputation, he's a liar. He's got a reputation for this.
当他有名声时，他就是个说谎者。他有此类名声。
He's also got a reputation for being a libertine.
他也有个别名，叫作业之人。
Okay? Meaning, like, he sleeps with men and women everywhere.
好的，...
Okay? And the Roman optimists,
...
okay, people who include Cato, Scipio,
521. 这是一句...
and Cicero, okay, these are the three most famous,
...
they hate Julius Caesar with a passion.
他们热爱朱利叶·凯撒。
They think Caesar represents all that's wrong with Rome.
他人们的...
He's a young man who has talent and charisma.
他是个年轻人，才华与风采。
And he's a genius of some sort.
他是一位风格...
But he's using it not for the glory of Rome,
但他把它用来做罗马的荣耀而已
but for his own personal political advancement.
...
Caesar represents to them the corruption of the Roman Republic.
Okay? And they develop, you can use this phrase,
OK? 这句...??
Caesar derangement syndrome.
Caesar 变...??
Okay? They have decided that they will do whatever they can to destroy this guy.
OK? 这...??
Okay? So Caesar wins a triumph,
OK? 先后??
and he wants to win the, and
and he wants towin the, and
he wants to get the consulship.
他想获得任意的任期
Okay? The problem is,
OK? 这句...??
you can only be a general to get the triumph,
你可以只做将军获得胜利，
but you have to give up your generalship in order to stand for election for the council.
但要把把军职归还给回去，才可得回归回去？
Okay? So the optimists give him a choice.
好的？于是乐观者给他一个选择。
You can either have the triumph, or you can have the consulship.
好的，乐观之选给他一个好时机
It's your choice. And they think, this guy, he's so good.
它是你的选择。 这位?? ?? ?? ?? ?? ??
He's so arrogant. He will never give up the triumph.
...
Okay? And Caesar surprises everyone by giving up the triumph.
好的？凯撒让大家惊讶，他把胜利交给了他。
He's like, I don't want this crap. I want to stand for election.
他像……………??
All right? So
好的？于是…
that's the other thing that's really surprising about Julius Caesar.
好的，...
He's unpredictable. Okay?
翻译结果
Or you can also argue
]}We need to translate cues 547 and 548. They are: [547] He's unpredictable. Okay? [548] Or you can also argue. Need toproduce JSON with translations array of two strings. Use simplified Chinese. Use line breaks if needed. Let's translate:
he understands the mentality
他理解对手的心态
or the motivations of his opponents.
或……??
But his opponents never understand him.
...
Okay? They always underestimate him.
好的，...
Okay? So Caesar is consul.
翻译结果
And as consul, he wants to do what everyone wants to do
好的...
and promote stability in Rome.
并在罗马促进稳定。
Okay? So he's promoting land reform. And here,
好的，...
the optimists try to obstruct him wherever they can.
Okay? The other thing is, after the consulship,
好的？另一件事是，任完执政后，凯撒想去占领高卢。
Caesar wants to go take over Gaul.
凯撒想去占领高卢。
Okay? And Gaul is a northern province in Rome.
好的，...
And there, he wants to win glory for himself.
在那儿，他想为自己赢得荣耀。
Okay? That's the plan.
好的？这就是计划。
The optimists understand this.
优化者们懂得很清楚。
And so beforehand,
先前，
they decide the next consul will be sent to Italy.
它们决定下一个执政者将被派往意大利。
Okay? Which is like basically Rome.
好的，
If you're in Rome, you can't fight wars.
如果你在罗马，你就能打不出战事。
You can't fight wars, you can't win glory.
你能打不出战事，能打不出??
You cannot triumph. Okay?
他…………??
And that's the idea. We'll let Caesar be consul,
并且如此，我们把把凯撒去做执政者
but we'll have him in Italy building roads
...】】】】】??
and cutting trees.
...??
Okay? We're not going to let him go fight wars in Gaul.
好的？我们不让他去高卢打仗。
That's for sure. Caesar knows about this.
确定！他也没得要去打仗！
And he does something that's really unexpected.
先前…………??
He forms an alliance with two other individuals
他与另外两位人物结成联盟
that the Senate hates.
他与两位已被上议院所喜的两位人物
Okay? The first is Pompey.
...
And Pompey is considered the greatest general of Rome.
安帕里被认为是罗马的最佳将军。
Okay? He's called Pompey the Great. And he's the one who's going to be the king of Rome.
安帕里被称为大帕里，且他将成为罗马的王。
And he's also pissed off the Senate because
安帕里还会给他先前…
Pompey the Great wins all these wars for Rome, and
帕米大帝赢得罗马的所有战争，随后他要安置他的老兵。
he has to settle his veterans.
他要给他那位老兵们给他给…
Right? He has to give land to his veterans, but the Senate refuses.
...
Okay? So Pompey's pissed off at the Senate as well.
好的？帕米也对参议院很不满。
And then there's Crassus. And
还有帕米的另一位伙伴，克拉苏。
Crassus is the richest man in Rome.
克拉苏是罗马最富有的那位。
He's the wealthiest man in Rome, and
他是罗马最富有的人，随后他又对参议院很不满，因为参议院阻塞了他很多政治生涯。
he's pissed off at the Senate as well because the Senate is blocking a lot of his political career.
好的，随后他又给了个别名。”】}We need to translate cues 588-590. Provide array of 3 translations. Ensure Chinese natural. Use preferred terms. Let's craft. 588:
Okay? So they form a secret alliance called the First Triumvirate.
589:
And so they do a lot of these deals.
于是他们签订了许多此类交易。
Okay? So Caesar, as council,
好吧？于是凯撒作为参议员，
will help settle the veterans of Pompey.
将帮助安抚帕米的老兵。
And he'll promote some tax reform that Crassus wants.
???
And in return, Pompey and
]}We need translate cues 594-596. Provide array of 3 translations. Ensure Chinese. Use line breaks. Let's craft. 594:
Crassus will give him Gaul as the promise
]}We need to produce translations. Let's produce Chinese. 594:
that he will take over once he leaves his country.
他将接管一旦离开本国后。
Okay? So that's the plan.
好吧？于是计划如此。
Okay? So when
好吧？于是当时。
Caesar becomes leader of Gaul,
???
the provincial governor of Gaul,
the procouncil from 58 to 51 BCE,
???
at this point,
在此时，
Caesar becomes a legend in Rome.
凯撒在罗马成为传奇。
Okay? This is where his myth -making genius really shines.
好的？这才是他造神话的天才所在。
He goes and commits genocide in Gaul, basically.
他去在高卢犯下大屠杀，基本上就是这样。
Okay? In the words of Caesar, I went to Gaul.
好吧？用凯撒的说法，咱们去高卢。
I killed a million Gauls in war.
我在战争里杀了百万人。
I enslaved a million Gauls.
我奴役了一百万人高卢人。
And then I let a million Gauls live.
然后我把百个高卢人活着放回去。
Okay? So he basically committed genocide against the Gauls.
好的，才是这句“高卢人”里？
And it was all for his personal glory.
它全是为了他个人的荣耀。
And he started all these wars in Gaul in order to accomplish three things.
他在高卢开始的所有战争都是为了完成三件事。
Okay? The first thing he wanted to do was money.
好的，先前方？
Okay? He got into a lot of debt because
好的？他因为要给很多人行贿以巩固自己的船队而负债累累。
he had to bribe a lot of people in order to secure his council ship.
他又要给他那句“回到回到”??
And he has to pay them off. Right?
...
So he made a lot of money.
译文1
The money that he had left over,
译文2
he sent back to Rome to organize feasts
译句
and festivals
和节日
for the Roman people. Okay? The term we use today is called bread and circus.
为罗马人准备的节日。好吧？我们今天用的词叫面包和圆盘。
Bread and circus. Okay?
面包圆盘
So that's what Caesar was doing in order to engrate himself with the Roman people.
于是，凯撒为此做了些事情，以便在罗马人中加深印象。
Okay? So that's the first major purpose of these wars.
好吧，咱们先给咱们的前后??
The second major purpose of these wars is to create the world's greatest army.
这点????????????????????????????????????????????????????
Remember, Rome is mainly at peace at this time.
记住，罗马此时正处于和平状态。
And if they're fighting wars, they're fighting wars against a lesser opponent.
而且一旦有战事，便是与之下级别的战事。
Okay? But Gauls are tough warriors.
好吧，格拉士们又是…
And the Roman,
...
his Roman soldiers are getting the best training in the world through eight years of constant fighting the Gauls.
Okay? So through this process,
...
he created the most loyal and the most disciplined army in the world.
他创建了世界上最忠诚、最有序列的军队。
And they're all loyal to him personally.
他又是……
Okay? Because he's the one rewarding them.
“…”，…
And he's the one who brings victory to them.
他是把胜利带给他们的那个人。
All right? The second thing. The third thing, which is the most important,
好的，...
is he creates the myth of Caesar as the great conqueror.
他在...
Okay? Romans loved generals.
好的？
Romans loved conquerors.
好的...
And while
...
Caesar was in Gaul fighting these wars,
凯撒在高卢战斗，他会把它们写成回报。
what he would do is he would write down dispatches or maybe reports.
凯撒在高卢战斗，他写下回报。
Right? Then he would send a soldier back to Rome.
凯撒在高卢战斗，**…**
And in the Forum of Rome, okay,
在罗马论坛里，好吧，
the main place, public place,
主打的主要位置，公之…
he would stand up and he would read the accomplishments of Caesar of that week.
他会在此处…
And the things he was doing was,
并且他所做的事，
I mean, it basically captured the imagination of Rome, of all Romans.
我想说它基本上把罗马的...
Okay? So for example, he attacked Germania.
好的？
Germania. And Romans thought the Germans were
德国。罗马人认为德国人是……
so barbaric, it was impossible to attack them. The second thing that
...
Caesar did to capture the imagination of Romans is he invaded Britain.
Britain in the imagination of Romans
英国在罗马人的想象中
was this mystical imaginary place.
是个神秘的...
And no one knew what it was.
...
And Caesar launched two major expeditions.
凯撒发起了两次大规模远征。
He launched two major expeditions against Britain that didn't really do anything.
他发起了两次大规模远征，去往往往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往去往
But that was not the point. The point was Caesar ventured into the unknown.
...
Okay? It's basically equivalent back then of the moon landing.
好的？那时的月球着陆的相当等价吗？
Does that make sense? It was just unheard of.
像是个…………………………………………………………??……………………...
Like, why would you go to Britain?
...
Aren't there like dragons in Britain?
在...??
Aren't there like sea monsters in Britain?
...
And Caesar went and went there twice.
Okay? So at this point,
OK? 这时...
he went to Rome.
他去罗马。
The Romans worship Caesar.
罗马人崇拜他。
Okay? Caesar's bribing them with like bread and circus.
???
And he's winning all these military exploits in Gaul. And
.
he's constructing a new reality of
他正在构建新的现实，凯撒为大…
Caesar as the great conqueror.
他正…
Okay? So does it make sense so far?
OK?
Okay? He's a myth maker. So
OK? 这位...??
while Caesar is doing this,
...
the optimists in Rome,
在...??
back in the day, they were like, in Rome, Cato, Scipio,
back in the day, they werelike, in Rome, Cato, Scipio,
and Cicero, they now see what a threat Caesar is.
...
They realize this guy's not beatable.
If he runs for elections,
...
he's going to win all the elections.
他将赢得所有选举。
His allies are going to win the elections. So
他的盟友将赢得选举。
they decide to strip him of his command,
他们决定把他从军职中剥夺，随后把他放在军职中...
of his military command, and put him on trial for all the things he did illegally.
...
Okay? And Caesar, he's not a nice person.
好的？凯撒不是个好人。他做了很多不合法的事。
He's done a lot of illegal things.
好的，凯撒………
Immoral things in order to accomplish power.
不道德的事以完成权力。
Right? So the Senate has a major case against him.
不道德…
And at this point, Caesar recognizes
在此时，凯撒意识到
that, listen, these guys mean war.
听着，...
So what Caesar does is he basically declares war on Rome.
于是，凯撒就把它们放在了...
He crosses the Rubicon. Okay?
...
And the Senate is appalled by this,
翻译1
and they appoint Pompey, who
翻译后...
again is considered the greatest general in Rome at this point,
?
to counter Caesar.
为了抵消凯撒。
Okay? And this starts the second civil war.
好，先说这件事。第二个…
The first civil war was between Sulla and Marius.
塞拉…
Okay? So
好的？那么
now it's Caesar versus Pompey.
现在是凯撒与庞波。
Any questions so far about this?
到目前为止，关于此事还有什么？
One quick question.
一个快速问题。
Sure. The two generals, they are...
好的，先说两位将军的事。
Oh, that's a great question.
哦，太好了！
Okay? So the Senate is about...
好的？所以参议院是关于……
It's about 300, 400 people.
它是300、400人左右。
It's a lot of people. Okay?
它是个大批人。
But the power in the Senate is not distributed equally.
但参议院的权力分布不均匀。
So if you are...
再想想吧！
So think of the Senate as maybe many circles.
先前的?
Okay? If you are the main...
好的？如果你是主角……
If you have the most power, you sit at the front.
如果你有最强的…
Why is that important? Because you're able to speak if you sit at the front.
...
Does that make sense? So even though technically, you're not allowed to speak, you're allowed to sit at the front.
当且...??
So intuitively, voting...
...
Everyone has the same voting rights.
The people at the front are those who are able to set the agenda and control the debate
在前面的人是能制定议程并掌控辩论的人
and make speeches. Everyone back here are not about to say anything.
在前面的人们………………………………………………………………
Okay? Because you go on turns. The people who
]}We need to produce translations for cues 717-719. Provide JSON array with three strings. Use Chinese terms. Let's translate each cue fully, with line breaks if needed. Ensure each string may contain at most one newline. Let's craft translations. Cue 717:
sit at the front are the optimists, because
...
they come from the most prestigious families, and they have the most illustrious political careers.
他们来自最有名望的家族，且拥有最辉煌的政治生涯。
Okay? Does that make sense? All right.
好的，...??
So when Caesar invades Rome...
在此时，凯撒…
He invades Rome. Basically, he declared war on the Roman Senate.
...
So let's look at a map of Rome at this time.
So let's look at a mapof Rome at this time.
This is the year 49 BCE.
This is the year49 BCE.
Right, so Rome is an empire. You have Italy here, this is Rome.
右 好！……………………………………………………
Over here is
...
basically Northern Africa.
Over here is Spain.
}]
Over here is Greece.
Over ... ... ... ... ... ... ... ... ... - ? ? ?? … … … … … ? … ?? … … … ... … 希 ... ? ? … .. .. 地图 .. ? ? ... .. ? ... .. ?? … .. 1 … … Over … .. .. .. .. .. ..… … … ... .. ... ... 地 … .. 希 .. .. ... … 中…… .. 希…… … … 翻 … .. ?? … … … Over … … 翻…… … … … JSON … … … … … … … ? … Over .. … 1…… … i……………………………………………………………………………
Over here is Anatolia, Syria.
Over ... ... ... ... ... 地 ... ... ... ... 地 ... ... 1 ... … … … … 中文 地…… ? … 地图 .. 先 … … 地……… 先…… 先…… 先…… … 先…… 先…… 先…… 先…地…… … 土 … ? … ?? … 地…… 土…… 先…… 地…地…………………………………………………………………………………
Okay, so that's the Roman Empire.
好的，...
Okay? At this point,
...
when Caesar crossed the River Cod,
当凯撒越过科德河时，
he controls basically Gaul, which is poor.
他控制的基本是高卢，只有一片贫穷的土地。
He controls Rome.
他控制着罗马。
The Ottomans and Pompeii.
奥托曼与波姆比。
They control Spain, Greece,
他们控制西班牙、希腊、安纳托利亚、叙利亚和北非。
Anatolia, Syria, and Northern Africa.
他们控制西班牙、希腊里亚、安纳托利亚里亚…
That's a problem for Caesar because, remember,
那是个…
Rome gets its food from the provinces.
...
Okay? So in other words, all Pompey has to do is wait.
好的？所以换句话说，帕姆波里只需等待。
This is what we call a containment strategy.
这就是我们所说的“等候”策略。
Containment strategy. Look,
看，封锁策略。
Caesar can't do anything, right?
Caesar...
And eventually, because Romans are starving, because
而且…
of this blockade, then the Romans will rise against Caesar.
…
Game over. Okay?
That's all the Ottomans have to do, just wait it out.
...
Over time,
Caesar will lose the loyalty of his troops
...
and of the Roman people. And then he will be weak.
和罗马人一起…然后他会变得很弱。
And then at that point, they're going to attack him.
然后在那时刻…他人们……
Okay? The war will be over. Does that make sense?
“…”，…
All right? So the odds are against Caesar
好的？所以，机会在这边，...
because he's basically one man.
因为…
Versus an entire empire.
…
Okay? But Caesar has two advantages.
好的？……
He has two major advantages.
好的……
The first advantage he has is he has,
again, the world's greatest military.
再次，世界上最伟大的军队。
Who have fought eight years in Spain.
他们在西班牙战斗八年。
They're extremely disciplined. They're extremely devoted to him.
他们很有纪律，且很忠于他。
Okay? That's the first major advantage.
好的？那是第一个主要优势。
The second major advantage is the division within the Ottoman Empire.
第二个主要优势是奥斯曼帝国的分裂。
The third major advantage is the great opposition. Okay?
第三个主要的优势是大约束。
Because even though the Ottomans,
因为即使奥斯曼人，
Cato and Cicero and Scipio, they don't really,
卡托、基多罗、斯基比奥，他们并不真正，
they hate Caesar.
卡托、基多罗、斯基比奥，他们的确是…
They don't trust Pompey either.
他们也不信任庞贝。
Right? Because as this war continues,
他/?????…
more and more power will accrue to Pompey.
更多的力量将不断归属于庞贝。
Right? He's going to have more and more power.
更多的力量归属给了古里…
So even though Pompey wants to drag this war out.
于是，庞贝想要把这场战争继续下去。
The Ottomans don't want this war to drag out.
奥尔顿们不想让这场战争继续下去。
They're afraid that, like even if Caesar,
他们怕，像是古里安…
as dictator, they will make Pompey the dictator.
...
Because the Ottomans, what they want to do is maintain the status quo.
因为奥尔顿们想保持现状。
They don't want a new king to arise.
因为奥尔顿们想要去…
They don't want a situation where Caesar loses but Pompey wins.
Okay? Does that make sense? So
...
the Ottomans are pushing Pompey to end the war as quickly as possible.
奥尔顿人正推动波姆佩尽快结束战争。
All right? And this division will be costly.
好的，波姆佩的分裂会有点儿…
In fact, it will basically be a war.
…
It will basically cost Pompey his life.
它会给波波尔...
So, given these two advantages,
...
the divisions within the Ottoman opposition
and given that Caesar has the world's greatest army,
和……因为凯撒拥有世界上最强的军队，
Caesar decides he must take the offensive.
凯撒决定他要去进攻。
Okay? So, first thing he does is he takes his army to Spain
好的？首先，他把军队调到西班牙并且...
and crushes all opposition in Spain.
好的，先...
When he crushes opposition in Spain, he does something that's not very Roman.
...
Okay? He offers clemency
好的，先...
to the enemy.
翻译到...??
Basically, he tells his enemies,
okay, we're all Romans.
好的，大家都是罗马人。
We're all fighting for the greater good of Rome.
我们都在为罗马的更好...
So, I've won this war.
...
Will you promise not to fight against me?
If you promise you won't fight against me anymore, I'll let you go.
如果你能给我一份...??
Okay? And when he did that, some...
...
Some of the Romans chose to just go home.
But there were also many who were like...
...
Who chose to go and fight for Pompey in Greece.
谁选择去在希腊战斗？
Okay? All right?
OK? 先前…
But that's what Julius Caesar is doing.
但这正是朱利叶·凯撒所做的事。
He's winning these wars against his opponents and he's letting them go.
他在赢得这场战斗…
He's forgiving them. So, that's the first thing that Caesar does.
他在原谅他们。于是，凯撒先做的事就是这样。
And then he marches to Greece. And again,
...
at this point, Pompey doesn't have to do anything.
在此时，波波里不必做任何事。
And Pompey doesn't want to do anything because he knows that Caesar has a lot of power.
在此时，波波里不必做任何事。”
He has a superior army. Okay? These are two of the greatest generals Rome has ever produced.
他拥有一支更强大的军队。好吗？这两位是罗马史上最伟大的将军之一。
Okay? Caesar and Pompey.
好吗？凯撒与波波里。
They understand each other. They understand warfare.
他们相互相识，能懂得军事。
And Pompey just wants to use the containment strategy and starve Caesar out.
波波里只想用围堵策略把凯撒逼到空中。
Caesar wants to fight a battle right away.
凯撒想立即战斗。
Okay? And what tips the balance is the Ottomans.
好的，...好吧！
Who force... Sorry.
谁来...抱歉。
The Ottomans. Cato, Scipio, and Cicero.
奥斯曼人。卡托、斯基比奥、奇科罗。
Who force Pompey to fight a battle.
谁把波波里打到战斗。”]}We need to translate cues 819-821. Provide Chinese subtitles. Use given terms. Let's translate each cue in order. Ensure each translation string may contain at most one newline. Use natural Chinese. Let's produce translations. Cue 819:
And... And in August 48 BCE,
...在公元前48年8月，两军在帕萨卢斯相遇。
at a place called Pharsalus, the two armies meet.
Okay? Pompey and Caesar.
...在公元前48年8月，两军在帕萨卢斯相遇。
Pompey chooses to use the anvil and hammer strategy.
帕萨卢斯之战：公元前48年8月，波波与凯撒相遇。
Remember what the anvil and hammer strategy is?
Where your infantry locks the enemy army into place.
帕萨卢**?**?】】】?
Okay? Locks it in place. And then from behind,
好的？把它锁定在位置。然后从后面，骑兵冲进来，扫掉敌方步兵。好的？这就是策略。亚历山大大帝的...
the cavalry comes in and wipes out the enemy infantry.
好的？从后面骑兵冲进来，骑兵冲进来…
Okay? That's the strategy. This is what Alexander the Great...
好的…
This is the strategy that Philip and
...
Alexander the Great used against the Greeks in Persia.
亚历山大大帝用它对付波斯的希腊人。
Okay? The problem is the...
好的？】】?】】
Julius Caesar's army is so disciplined and
朱利叶·凯撒的军队如此有序且经验丰富，足以抵御骑兵冲锋。
so experienced that they withstood the cavalry charge.
朱利叶·凯撒的军队有序列，能胜一骑士…
And they wiped out the army at Pharsalus.
在帕萨卢斯战役中，军队被消灭。
Okay? Then,
好的，...
Caesar took his army to Egypt, conquered that.
凯撒把军队带到埃及，征服了那儿。
To Syria, conquered that. And to Anatolia, conquered that.
至今可归一…
Okay? The Senate asked for a report from Caesar.
好的？参议院请他报告。
Like, how's the war going? What's happening?
好的，...
Okay? And Caesar said the most famous line that he ever said.
好的？凯撒说了他最著名的一句。
And again, he's a myth -making genius. Right?
好的，...
He basically said, Vinni vedi vici.
他基本说：维尼·维迪·维奇。
Okay? Beautiful Latin.
好的，...
The most powerful Latin phrase ever spoken in human history.
最强大的拉丁语短句，已在人的历史上说过。
It means, I came,
它是说：我来过，...
I saw, I conquered.
其后…
Okay? And again, this captured the imagination of the Roman people.
OK?
After Caesar calmed the Roman ease,
...
he goes to Africa to fight Cato
and Scipio at the Battle of Phasis.
和斯基比奥在帕西斯战役中。
Okay? And again, Caesar wants to show clemency.
好的，回到…
He wants to show how generous and merciful he is.
他想展示他多么好，…
But at this point, his soldiers, who are getting very old,
他想展示…
they just want this war to end, and they want to go home.
他们只想这场战争结束，才会…
So at this battle, what they do is,
…
they defy the orders,
他们违抗命令，
direct orders of Caesar not to engage.
他们直接发出指令…
They took it upon themselves to attack the enemy.
他们自己主动攻击敌人。
And at this point, they're winning the war, right?
他们在此时已胜利。”
They're winning the battle. Caesar orders them to show mercy.
他们在此战中已胜利。凯撒下令让他们示恩。
The veterans, his veterans,
“古”??…
massacre their enemies to ensure they can't fight back again.
在此处，敌人占据山丘。
Okay? The last battle is in Spain at the Battle of Manda.
And here, the enemy is on a hill.
在此处…
And you're not supposed to fight uphill.
并且你们不必上坡去作战。
Okay? You're not supposed to go up a hill and fight the enemy there because you're at a major disadvantage, right?
好吧，先前……
Caesar's soldiers now are so experienced and disciplined that they can do that.
他……
They can just march up the hill and destroy the enemy.
他们可以直接上山丘并消灭敌人。
Okay? So that's how powerful Caesar's enemy,
好吧，先前…
sorry, that's how powerful Caesar's army is at this point.
他们的军队在此时刻…
They basically wipe out every army they fight against.
他们基本上去掉了每个战斗的军队。
Like, we conquer the Roman Empire.
...
Okay? Does that make sense?
Caesar goes back to Rome in 44.
凯撒在44年回到罗马。
And this is the year he will be assassinated by his friends.
他在此年回到罗马并回到回到回到回到回到回到回到回到回到回到回到回到回到回到回到回到回...
He launches legislative reform to reform the Roman Republic.
...
Okay? He launches land reform.
好的？他启动了陆权改革。
He launches debt relief.
他启动了债务减免。
He creates something called the Julian calendar.
他创造了一个叫朱利安历法的东西。
The Julian calendar is what we still use today.
朱利安历法是我们现在使用的那种日历。
Before Julius Caesar, the Romans used the lunar calendar.
前方...??...??????????????????????????????????????????????????…
And then Julius Caesar, working with astronomers,
...????...????…
they designed together the Julian calendar, which is exactly what we still use today.
他们一起设计了朱利安历法，正好是我们现在使用的那种日记
Okay? That's a major reform. He offered clemency.
好的？那是一次大改革。他给了赎回。
To all his enemies. Basically,
好的...????????????????????????????????????????…
if you're willing to work for the good of Rome,
如果你愿意为罗马的好事工作，他会把他回到参议院里！
he will invite you back into the Senate.
如果你先前……
Okay? He offered citizenship
...
to his soldiers
and to Italians.
...
Okay? He brought in citizenship in Rome.
好的，...??…
So what Caesar was doing was,
he was basically trying to resolve a lot of the contradictions
that led to instability
]}
and civil war and revolution in Rome before then.
...
Okay? And he was successful.
好的？他成功了。
And he was considered a genius.
他又被认为是个 ...
He was loved by the people. In fact, he was everywhere.
他深受百姓喜爱，实际上他无处不在。
He had busts of himself everywhere.
他在各处都有立像。
Okay? And he, and then he made it, he minted coins,
好的？他又把它做成了，...
money, that has, that has his face on it.
好的，...
So he was basically creating what we call a cult of personality. Okay?
于是他基本上在创造我们所说的个人崇拜。好吗？
And he wanted to continue to expand the Roman Empire.
他想继续扩张罗马帝国。
His plan was to go fight a place called Parthia,
他的计划是去打仗帕提亚，它是古老的波斯帝国。
which is the old Persian Empire.
他的计划是去打仗帕帕里亚…
And then he wanted to go conquer Germania.
然后他想去征服高卢。
Okay? He basically wanted to conquer the entire world.
好的？他基本上去征服整个…
That was his ambition. His ambition was to make Rome great again.
那是他的雄心。他的雄心就是把罗马再度成大国。
And he almost succeeded,
而且他几乎成功了，
except ultimately he was killed by his friends.
他终于在回到点…
He was assassinated in 44 BC.
他在公元前44年被暗杀。
Okay? So,
好的？所以，
let's look at those three questions again.
再看一次这三问。
Okay? First of all, what motivates Caesar?
好的？首先，是什么驱使凯撒？
Second question is, why did he succeed?
第二个问题是，为什么他成功？
The third question is, why did they kill him? Okay?
第三个问题是，为什么他被杀了？
So, I think what motivated him is exactly what motivated someone like Sulla,
所以，我认为他之所以动机正是像苏拉、马里乌斯以及其他罗马伟将的动机。
and Marius, and other great generals of Rome.
他们想让罗马再度一回去！
They wanted to make Rome great again.
其后??
They're nostalgic for the Rome of the Hannibal Wars.
他们回想汉尼拔战争时期的罗马
Right? When everyone came together and
当时大家一起…
made the sacrifice necessary in order to protect and save Rome.
当时…
They wanted to return to that era.
他们想回到那个时代。
Okay? And that's what motivated him.
好吧？ 这就是他动机的前景！
He didn't want to become king.
他不想成为王！
And if he became king, he didn't want to stay as king.
如果他成为王，他就会把它当作一件好事。
Remember, Sulla won the war, and he could have made himself king.
回到……
But he didn't do that.
先后……
He implemented a lot of reforms, and then he retired.
他实施了许多改革，随后退休。
Because that was the Roman way.
因为那是罗马之道。
Okay? That's what the ancestors did.
好吧？ 这是古人所作的！
And he wanted to be loyal to the gods, to the ancestors,
他想要忠于神祇、祖先与罗马。
and to Rome. Okay?
他在此时刻…
So, Caesar didn't want to become king.
...
He just wanted to save Rome.
他只想拯救罗马。
Second question then is,
第二个问题是，
how is he able to succeed?
他能怎样成功？
And this is a more difficult question.
和这更难的问句。
Okay? So, again, the argument is he's a myth maker.
好吧，回到…
What does that mean? Okay.
先前的…
So, there are different individuals in society
于是，社会中出现了不同的人物，推动社会的善事。
that promote the social good.
好的？他们能在社会各个方面完成大事。
Okay? Or they're able to accomplish great things in different aspects of society.
The first is a general, right?
第一个是将军，没错吧？
The general. The general,
将军将军，
he is bold and disciplined.
他是将军，且是个大把手
And he's fair. Right?
他也很公平。对吗？
That's why the soldiers follow him.
这就是为什么士兵们跟随他。
He's bold, he's disciplined, and he's fair.
他很大胆，且有纪律，且很公平。
He's also concerned about organization
他也关注组织和后勤。
and logistics.
How do you move an army from place to place?
他也关注组织和后勤。
How do you feed your army? Okay?
怎样给军队供给？好吗？
That's what the general does.
那就是军师的工作。
That's what a great general does. That's what Hannibal did.
那就是大军师的工作。那是汉尼拔的工作。
Okay? Then you have the politician.
...
And the politician, he's basically like an avatar of the people.
He's able to capture and represent the emotions
...
and the dreams and the longings of the people.
和人民的梦想与渴求。
Okay? He's very charismatic.
好的？他很有魅力。
And he's very manipulative.
而且他很有操纵性。
Okay? He's able to tell stories that
好的？他能讲述故事，能让人们的情感想象力...
capture the emotional imagination of the people.
好的，能说……
That's what the politician does.
...
Then you have the administrator.
然后你有管理员。
Or the legislator. Okay?
或者说是管理员。 ？
And this person is very concerned about details.
而且此人很关心细节。
And law and legal aspects.
和法律与法制方面。
Okay? Regulation. And the person,
好的？ 规章与人…
you can say, is almost a systems design thinker.
又是个…
Very big picture.
很大图景。
Very macro. Trying to figure out how the different pieces fit together.
很大图景…………
If you think about it, these three individuals,
??
the general, the politician, and the administrator,
将军、政治家与行政者，将军、立法者，他们是不同的个性。他们彼此相互相冲。
the legislator, they're very different personalities.
将军、政治家与行政者，将军与立法者，都是相互相冲的。
They're in contradictions with each other.
??
So, for example, Pompey was a great general,
比如说，庙庙…
but he was a terrible, terrible politician.
...
Okay? Hannibal was a great general, too.
But he was not of a good general.
]????????????????????????????????????????……?????????略…?????…???…?????…??…??-??..?????…??…???…???…??-??..??????………??…??-…?????…???…??………??…………??……………??……………??……………??……………??……………??………..??…..???……..??…………………………??……..??…..???…………………………??……..??…..
He was a great legislator. The thing
. 1?..??..???…..???…..??..???…..??..???…..??..
that made Julius Caesar
that made JuliusCaesar
distinctive is he
...
was all three together.
??
Okay? Because
...
what enables you to be all three together is the imagination.
That was Julius Caesar's secret power.
那是朱利亚·凯撒的秘密力量。
His imagination. He was able to imagine himself as different people at once.
他的想象力。他能一次多重归一人。
And therefore, he was different people at once.
...
He had multiple personalities.
他有多重人格。
And that's why he was so unpredictable.
That's why he was able to understand the motivations of his opponents.
...
And that's why he was able to accomplish so much.
Okay? Does that make sense?
好的？这有道理吗？
Okay? And so, he became a myth maker.
好的？然后，...又是个回归作的??
The problem is, he was a myth maker. The problem with being a myth maker is you ultimately have to change reality.
翻译1
And by changing reality,
翻译2
you make people who are accustomed to reality uncomfortable.
你让人们习惯的那点点点...??
Okay? And
]}
so, that's why he was killed.
so, 这是个...??
He was killed by not his enemies, but by his friends.
...??
Okay? So, there were four major conspirators against Julius Caesar.
译文1
They were Decimus Brutus,
译文2
who is basically, who
谁是基本的，谁
was basically Caesar's lieutenant in war.
谁是基本的...
You had Trebonius, again, the major lieutenant of Caesar.
你有特布尼乌斯，另外还有凯撒的主要副将。
But you also had Cassius.
但你也有卡西乌斯。
Cassius was actually fighting for Pompey.
卡西乌斯其实是为帕蒙的战斗。
But Caesar thought he was such a great general that Caesar pardoned him.
但凯撒认为他是个大将军，凯撒又给他一回去！
Okay? And you also had Marcus Brutus.
OK????????????????????????????????????????…
Who Caesar actually saw as a son.
????…??????????????…??…??………??…??…??…??………………………………………………………………………??…………??………??…??…??………??………JSON…??………………………………………………………{
Okay? So, these are the people who are closest to Caesar.
好的？所以，这些人是最接近凯撒的人。
And they ultimately killed Caesar.
而且最终把他杀了。
Because even though Caesar was making Rome better,
因为即使凯撒在做好事，
he was changing Rome. Which
他正在改变罗马！
caused them to feel uncomfortable and anxious about the future of Rome.
??
Okay? Does that make sense? So, an analogy is this.
Let's just say that one day, the Chinese government says,
我们先说，某一天，中国政府宣布，
we're going to outlaw rice.
白米将被列为法定品。
White rice. Because
白米之所以有此举是因为
white rice has proven to be scientifically bad for you.
白米已被证明对你们有科学上的好处。
Okay? It's not nutritious for you.
好的，白米不吃就能吃好吃的吃吃？
Instead, we're going to make every Chinese eat steak and potatoes and broccoli.
此时…
So that Chinese can be strong and healthy.
让中国人强壮健康。
Okay? How would Chinese feel about this?
好，~?~?
They'd be pissed. Okay?
...
Do you understand? So, you know, it's unfortunate that Caesar did nothing wrong.
你知道吗？ 这就好吧…
And everything that Caesar did was for the good of Rome.
...……
But change,
reform, causes cognitive dissonance.
改革，产生认知失调。
Okay? It makes people anxious and uncomfortable.
好的？它会让人们产生焦虑与舒适。
Okay? It disrupts your identity.
好的？它会给我方位的方位。
And that's why there's a conspiracy
...……
that ultimately killed Caesar.
Okay? Does that make sense?
...……
Okay? How did Caesar challenge the Roman identity?
好的？凯撒是怎样挑战罗马身份的？
Okay. Okay.
好的。好的。
So, the question, how did Caesar challenge the identity of being Roman?
于是，问题是：凯撒是怎样挑战罗马身份的？
Okay. That's a great question.
好的。很好的问题。
All right. So, let's look at his reforms.
好的，先看一下他的改革。
First of all, he had a Julian calendar, right?
首先，先前有个百月历。
The Julian calendar. So,
朱利安历法。于是，
he was challenging people's sense of time, time.
他挑战了人们对时间的感知。
You understand? So, before he was a Roman, he was a Roman.
你明白吗？
Before he had the lunar calendar, now you have the Julian calendar.
在他使用月历之前，现在你们使用朱利安历法。
Second thing that he did was he was doing all this stuff by himself.
第二点是他自己做了这些事情。
Okay? He was winning these military victories by himself.
好的？他自己赢得了这场胜利。
He was introducing much reform legislation by himself.
他自己引入了许多改革法案。
He was a great man. But if you're Roman,
他是个大人物。若是罗马人，
what you have been taught is these three ideas.
他所学的三种思路
Piety, liberty, and republica,
虔诚、自由与共和国，
which is to say no one is above Rome.
它是说一切皆为罗马之下。
Everyone is equal in the eyes of Rome.
人人在罗马眼中等同。
This general who
这位将军，
won against Hannibal or Carthage or the Greeks,
赢了哈尼伯或卡尔塔格之战，
it wasn't because he was a great man.
它不必是因为他是个大人物。
It was because he was fighting for Rome.
翻译1：...
Okay? Okay.
翻译后...
So, the fact that Julius Caesar was a genius,
…
that he was so brilliant
1062. 译文1
and he was able to accomplish so much, it made them jealous, right?
1063.. 译文2..??
It made people jealous. But at the same time,
? 1??????..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??.....?????..??..??..
it made them see him
它让他们把他视为罗马稳定的威胀
as a threat to the very stability of Rome.
它们的...???
Does that make sense? Because people like Julius Caesar aren't supposed to exist.
翻译后????
Rome does not need kings.
...
In fact, Rome is anti -monarchy.
Okay? So, they're very much afraid
...
that Julius Caesar thought himself as a god
and he was making himself king.
翻译后...???
And in fact, Julius Caesar,
?
I mean, had hubris, right?
我说，若有自负，才是吧？
Obviously, if you believe that you by yourself can change Rome, you have hubris.
我说，若...
But he was right. Caesar was not showing enough deference to the Senate.
但他是对的。凯撒没有向参议院充分致敬意。
He was creating a cult of personality.
他在做一个很好的！
He was being very arrogant.
他很自以为豪。
It seemed very much like he wanted to become king.
它们好像是...
Does that make sense? So
译文1
there's a lot of evidence to suggest that Caesar wanted to become king.
译文2
And that's what made them uncomfortable.
翻译1
What I'm saying is
翻译2
the real issue is the idea of carnal dissonance.
翻译1
Where the very existence of Caesar challenged the perception of what Rome was
翻前后??
and what Rome meant. Does that make sense?
...
But very good question, okay. Any more questions?
翻译1
Crassus. Oh,
翻译2
okay. So Pompey
OK 先后??
and Crassus and Caesar,
?
how did they form their alliance?
...????????...
Okay, so the first thing to understand is
...????????..
Pompey and Crassus were both optimists.
波贝和克拉苏都是乐观派。
They were supporters of Sulla.
他们是苏拉的支持者。
Remember, Sulla is the one who crushed the populars.
记得，苏拉是那个把民粘打败的。
So Pompey and Crassus were conservatives.
再来，波贝尔·波普里亚里？
They were optimists. Caesar was a populier.
他们是乐观派。凯撒是民粘。
So the alliance was secret.
所以，合并发了。”
It was completely unexpected. And that's why they were able to accomplish so much.
完全意外的，正是这点让他们能完成这么多事。
Because politically, they were at odds with each other.
因为在政治上，彼此相互相冲突。”
The reason why they formed an alliance is
他们结盟的原因是基本上是机缘巧合。
just basically expedience.
波普里亚里有个要点要通过塞内特里。”
Pompey had issues that he wanted to pass through the Senate.
他又能很久久的…
Crassus had issues that he wanted to pass through the Senate and Caesar as well.
克拉苏也想把事发到参议院去，跟着也有个…
So they decided it would be politically expedient to work together.
再把它们…………………
And that's the genius of Caesar, okay?
……………………
He's very charismatic.
他很有魅力。
He's very manipulative. So
他很有变幻。
he was able to form an alliance with people
他能通过…
who were technically his enemies, okay?
谁是他的技术敌人，好的？
Pompey and Crassus were his enemies.
庙帕姆·克拉苏是他的敌人。
They were politically at odds with him.
他们在政治上与他相对立。
But Caesar was able to put aside political differences
但可萨尔能把政治差异放在一边
and form an alliance for the sake of interest and expediency.
但可萨古尔...??
Does that make sense? But obviously this would not last very long.
...
Any more questions?
1116. 还有什么问题吗？
Okay. Okay.
1117.. 先后??
Okay, so next class, we're gonna look at the world
1111?
that Caesar created.
那可萨尔创建的...??
Because after he dies, the Republic falls.
...???
So we will look at what happens after he dies
...????
and look at the birth of the Roman Empire,
...
okay? So many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many many